<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse vpon the libertie or captivitie of the Kyng 1562.</title>
            <title>Discours sur la liberté ou captivité du roy. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1562</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18478</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5034</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111044</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846471</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846471</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11440</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18478)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11440)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 190:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse vpon the libertie or captivitie of the Kyng 1562.</title>
                  <title>Discours sur la liberté ou captivité du roy. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henry Sutton for Edvvarde Sutton dvvelling in Lumbard strete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Lo[n]don :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1562]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Discours sur la liberté ou captivité du roy [1562], an anonymous work about the supposed captivity of Charles IX.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The libertie or capiuitie of the king.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A B⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  IX, --  King of France, 1550-1574 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11440:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>A DISCOVRSE vpon the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <hi>or capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie of the Kyng.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1562.</p>
                  <p>Imprinted at Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don by Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sutton for Edvvarde Sutton dvvelling in Lumbard ſtrete.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11440:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11440:2"/>
            <head>A DISCOVRSE VP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the libertie or capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie of the Kyng.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>PON</hi> the letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes publyſſhed vnder the Kynges name, the viii. of Apryl, in the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che it is ſayde, that there runneth a bruite through this realme, the king and the Queene his mother, ſhoulde bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte their pleaſure withholden and caried where it ſhould ſeme good to ſome princes and lordes that are aboute their Maieſties: but yet that the ſame reporte is an vntrewe and falſe ſclaunder: for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as muche as their perſonnes are in the ſame libertie that at all tymes they haue been: it hath been thoughte good to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyſſhe this ſmalle diſcourſe, to the ende that thereby the ſubiectes of the Kynge myghte the more cleerely vnderſtande, and put their myndes oute of all doubte and cumbre, whereby they maye yealde vnto hym that obedience and feaultie,
<pb facs="tcp:11440:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> which they owe vnto hym lyke good and faithfull ſubiectes of his maieſtie.</p>
            <p>Euerye man knoweth the enterpriſe that the laſt wynter was taken in hande for the hauynge the Duke of Orleaunce out of this Realme: menne knowe alſo bothe by whome and to what ende the ſame was doone. But leaſt thoſe whome this matter toucheth ſhoulde complayne as though men in the report offred them wrong: we wyll ſimply ſette beefore all men the wytneſſe and depoſition of the ſayde yong Duke of Orleaunce: vppon the whiche we wyll ſtay our ſelues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preiudice of his authoritie: leauynge to them that ſhall fynde themſelues gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, libertie to attempt the diminiſhyng of his credite, as to them ſhal ſeme good. The tenor of the ſaid depoſition is thus. The Saterday whiche was the daye his maieſtie began firſt to come oute of his chaumber after the recouerie frome his ſyckneſſe, the Duke of Orleance being in the kynges chaumbre, the duke of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours came vnto hym, who aſked hym, whether he were a Hugenot or a Papiſt. Whereunto the Duke of Orleaunce
<pb facs="tcp:11440:3"/> anſwered, that he was of the religion of the Quene his mother. Than ſayde the Duke of Nemours, myght it not pleaſe you that I ſpake vnto you halfe a doſeyn of wordes? The other aunſwered (yes.) The duke of Nemours than tooke hym aſyde vnto a coffre whyche was nere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the doore of the kynges bedchambre. and ſayde vnto hym. Syr I ſee the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme of Fraunce is vndoone and ruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by theſe Hugenots, and the Kynge and you bee not in ſuretie: becauſe the kynge of Nauarre, and the Prynce of Conde wylle make theym ſelues kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and wyll ſo handle the mattier as they wylle bothe cauſe the Kynge and you to bee putte to deathe. Syr yf you wyll auoyde this daunger, it is nedefull, that you doo well aduyſe your ſelfe. And yf you wylle, the houſe of Guyſe and I wylle healpe and ſuccoure you, and wylle ſende you eyther into Lorayne or Sauoye. The Duke of Orleaunce an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered that he would not leaue the king nor the quene his mother: The other yet replyed therto, ſaying, Aduiſe your ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:11440:4"/> well of that I tell you. For it is for your aduantage. Wherevnto the other ſayde nothyng. Than ſayd vnto hym the duke of Nemours: Doo you not verye well truſte Carnaualet and Villarquier? Yes ſayd he. Than ſayd the other: Tel them nothyng of this I haue ſayde vnto you, nor of the purpoſe I haue ſo long holden with you: but if they aſke you what it was that I ſayde vnto you, tel them that I tolde you of certayne playes and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies. and ſo the ſaid duke of Nemours lefte hym. While this was a doyng, the duke of Guyſe (who ſtandyng afore the fyre, talked with his ſonne the prince of Ginuille) perceyuynge that the Duke of Nemours hadde left the Duke of Orle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce, came towardes hym and ſayde: Syr I haue hearde ſaye, that the Quene wyll ſende the Duke of Aniew and you, into Lorayn to a verye faire caſtell, that you maye there take the ayre: Vppon condicion that you would come thyther, we woulde make you good cheere there. Whereunto the Duke of Orleance an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered: I do thynke the Quene my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther woulde not that I ſhould leaue the
<pb facs="tcp:11440:4"/> Kyng. Wherevnto the prince of Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uille replyed, ſayeng: If you wyll come into Lorayne, and thynke vppon that whiche the Duke of Nemours hath ſayd vnto you, it will come you well to paſſe. The Duke ſayd nothing thervnto. The morowe after, the prince of Gynuille came agayne towardes the Duke, and ſayde vnto hym the ſelfe ſame that he had doone before, addyng further, that yf he would vnderſtande the meane how they woulde carye hym away, he would tell hym. The duke aunſwered, that he woulde gladely learne it. The prince of Gynuille ſayd: They wyll carie you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way euen whan it is mydnyght, and wil helpe you to comme oute at a wyndowe, whyche is ryght ouer the brydge in the parke, and immediately they wyll ſette you in a coche, and ſo ſhall you bee in Lorayn afore any man bee ware there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. The Duke aunſwered nothyng here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, and ſo he lefte the ſaid prince. The morowe after, the duke of Nemours de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, and came to take his leaue of the kyng. and in takynge leaue, ſayde vnto the Duke in his eare: bethynke you of
<pb facs="tcp:11440:5"/> that I haue ſayde, and tell no body ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And ſo the ſayde Duke of Nemours went on his way. This conſpiracie hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penyng al togither otherwiſe than thoſe, whiche are reckened the heades and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors thereof looked for: it is nat to bee meruayled at, if men of a long tyme ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in the feats of warre, ſeeynge they had nothyng profited by theſe am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſſhes and coouert enterpriſes (nor yf I maye ſo terme theym) by theſe vnder grounde woorkes, yf they determyned to entre by open force and manyfeſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, as men doo into a ſtrong holde or towne. Natwithſtandyng yet to be ſure of a backe doore (as the prouerbe ſayth, leaſte happelye theyr ſeconde attempte myghte ſpeede as euyll as the fyrſte: The houſe of Guyſe (who a long whyle afore hadde written to one of the greateſt princes of Germanie, and one of that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion whyche is called Proteſtant, to entreate hym to enter with theym into ſomme conference of the Auſburgh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, wherein they gaue hym ſomme hope they woulde gladly bee inſtructed)
<pb facs="tcp:11440:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> wente theyr wayes into Lorayne, and frome thence to a lyttell towne neede vnto the Rhyne called Sauerne: In the whyche place they hadde ſuche communication with the ſayd prince the fyftenthe, ſyxtenthe, and ſeuententhe of Februarye, as after they hadde all promyſed to folowe the Relygion of the Goſpell: In the ende the ſayde Duke of Guyſe (in token of the fauour he bare to that Religion) prayed hym to doo ſo mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che with the other Proteſtantes princes, that for as muche as of olde auncientie the houſe of Lorayne hadde bene of the Empyre: By that meane, bothe hee and his bretherne, myghte alſo bee aduowed as Prynces of the Empyre, hauynge theyr voyces and conſentes in all Commyſſyous Imperyall, that by that meane they myghte withdrawe and exempte theym ſelues frome vnder the kynges ſubiection: offryng theimſelues to ſigne and ſubſcribe vnto the ſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſyon of Awſburghe, and that they woulde putte theym ſelues in the rolle and numbre of the ſayde Proteſtantes.
<pb facs="tcp:11440:6"/> Wherevnto the ſayd prince was ſo wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng to putte to his healpyng hande (ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng by this meane to wynne the ſayde houſe of Guiſe to the religion of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell) as he fayled not to put foorthe the ſame in a dyete, a lyttell whyle after hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by ſundry of the ſayde princes in the toune of Brouxell, about the begynning of Marche folowyng. and was neuer the leſſe refuſed of the other princes for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, but chiefly by reaſon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> newes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> horrible bouchery of Vaſſy: as the ſayde prince ſince that tyme hath expreſly wryten vnto the ſayd Duke of Guyſe: ſendynge hym woorde that the ſayd companie was muche offended and prouoked againſt him by occaſyon of that cruell murther: and prayed hym that he woulde ſende hym the trewe certaintie with a full declaration of his intent and purpoſe therin without any diſguyſing: For ſuche are the propre woordes of his letter. Vpon this departyng frome the court, in taryeng while the winter ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed, it was determyned betwene the ſayde Duke of Guyſe, the Conſtable, and marſhall ſaynct Andrewe, that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng
<pb facs="tcp:11440:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> their abſence euery one of theym ſhould practiſe with the greateſt numbre of gentlemen, and other men of warre as muche as in theim lay, to cauſe theim meete togyther in armes at Nantheull, and neere to Parys aboute the laſte of wynter in the moneth of Marche.</p>
            <p>This practiſe coulde not bee ſo cloſely conueyed, but that the Quene was quick<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly aduertiſed thereof, not onely by ſome of this realm, but alſo by certain ſtrange princes: Who could ſo well appoynt her the tyme as they tolde her afore hande, that it was in the month of Marche, that execution woulde bee done: yea (that more is) a certaine gentleman ſtranger, gaue the kynge of Nauarre ſo ſure fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokens, as he tolde hym that they would go about to wynne hym to thintent they myghte helpe themſelues with hys title and authoritye for a ſeaſon, but in the ende laughe hym to ſcorne: Wherupon the ſayd kynge of Nauarre brought hym to the Queene to cauſe her vnderſtande the ſayde aduertiſementes, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue her from ſuche enterpriſes. Well, this practiſe neuertheleſſe goyng on for
<pb facs="tcp:11440:7"/> the beehoufe of the ſayde kynge of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre (and GOD wyll) Thoſe vnto whome the appoyntemente was geuen, fayled not to fynde theym ſelues with all their force in tyme and place: ſo as the ſayde Duke of Guyſe commynge to Nantheull at the appoynted ſeaſon, was by and by mette with the Conſtable, the Duke of Aumale, the Marſhall Saincte Andrewes and others of theyr faction: Among whome were the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of Mezieres, and of Courtenaye, by whome men maye coniecture the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryllous poynte and daungerous enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe: by this that makynge theym rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye to go to the place of this aſſemble, they putte theym ſelues in ſuche ordre as like perſonnages are wonte to dooe when they ſhall entre the battayle or any daungerous aduenture: ſhriuynge them ſelues to a prieſte, and receyuyng theyr houſell (as it is reported) after they hadde well and deuoutely hearde theyr Maſſe.</p>
            <p>Whyle this was in hande the prouoſt of the Marchauntes of Parys (who is one of the principall myniſters and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentes
<pb facs="tcp:11440:7"/> of this faction) hadde ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered all mattiers, and prepared the waye to brynge theſe troupes into the towne of Parys, that the quene beeyng aduertiſed, that theyr determynation was for to goe thyther, ſente ſundrye tymes vnto the ſayd duke of Guyſe that he woulde comme to her in her houſe at Monceaulx, where he ſhuld be very wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, forbyddyng hym expreſſly the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traunce into Parys with ſuche a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, meanyng thereby to auoyde thoſe troubles and inconueniences whych ſhe foreſawe woulde come to paſſe: ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remembryng the execution and bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherye newely commytted in the towne of Vaſſy: vppon the whiche moſte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantely menne cryed for Iuſtice to the Kyng and her, who harde nothynge but Playntes and Lamentations in euery place where they wente in this Realme concernyng that crueltie. Hytherto than it appeareth, that this enterpriſe of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng on armour, was apoynted on, long afore hande by the duke of Guiſe as the Quene her ſelfe, &amp; the kyng of Nauarre were right well informed: for the day of
<pb facs="tcp:11440:8"/> meetyng was iuſtly kepte: wherein men came thether from all partes in open ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and order fitte for the warr: where as before their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to gether, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme was in a deepe reſte and quietneſſe: tyll ſuche tyme as harneſſe was putte on contrarye to the kynges proclamations, and ſo continued againſt the expreſſe ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and prohibicion of the Queene ſo often renued: Finally tyll the ſayd Duke of Guiſe made his entre into Paris, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen armes againſt the very countremou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyngs and forbiddyngs by the Kyng and the Queene his mother.</p>
            <p>Nowe lette vs ſee what folowed. The aboueſayde capitaynes of this armye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge at Paris, they beganne to holde a councell as though the ſame hadde bene a councell royall: makyng to aſſemble the preſydentes, the councellours, the kynges officers, the ſhriefes or hed offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Toune, euen as though they had had the kynges Superioritie in their handes, notwithſtandyng that the quene were nothynge at all aduertiſed hereof, neyther that ſhe had any vnderſtanding or communication with that whiche paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:11440:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> in the ſaid councel, ſo as her will &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyntmente whiche ſhe had determined to go on with her voyage towardes the toune of Bloys increaſed with her more and more: to thend ſhe myght withdraw her ſelfe to ſome place where ſhe ſhoulde nat be compelled: if happly the reportes and aduertiſements which ſhe had harde afore ſhould be founde true.</p>
            <p>Now are we come preſently to the knot and chiefe poynte of this queſtion. For the Quene who was with the Kyng, and the duke of Orleance her children in his houſe of Fountainbleu, and beeyng in her way towardes Orleance, goyng on of her iorney, hauyng ſent folkes to Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boiſe to cauſe the yong Duke of Aniow her ſonne to be brought vnto her to Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaunce: and hauynge no force in the worlde aboute her, neither of horſeman nor of footeman: ſodeynely arriued the forſaid capitains of this enterpriſe with an armie of horſemen in faire armure, &amp; planted themſelues afore the ſaid Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainbleau, and rounde about. Nowe I aſke thoſe that vnder the kynges name publyſhe thoſe letters patentes, whereof
<pb facs="tcp:11440:9"/> afore mencion is made, whether, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe a yong kyng of the age of a leuen or twelue yeares beyng onely accompanied wyth hys mother and hys little brother with piſtolyers, &amp; harquebuſiers, be not properly the ſame thing, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in good ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes men call (the beſieging of the kyng) or yf that terme miſlyke theym, what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worde they coulde deuiſe for the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng of ſuch an acte?</p>
            <p>But let vs be content yet that all thys bee eſteemed as a thynge of none impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. We wyll onely ſee what folowed of this ſiege layde afore Fontaynbleau, it is well knowen that the Queene aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng conſtantlye in this her pleaſure to goe to Orleans and deſyryng to make thytherwarde: Great importune inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, to muche vnworthy of her maieſtye, was made vnto her, to cauſe her tourne hed, and come backe her way to returne to Melune. Men knowe alſo that ſhe her ſelfe perſuadyng with teares the naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye aire and other reaſonable cauſes of her refuſall, dydde a greate whyle wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande the departyng from the ſaid foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainebleau: declaring vnto theim there
<pb facs="tcp:11440:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> was no cauſe why they ſhoulde geue the kyng ſuche an alarm. Menne knowe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that the kyng ſeyng hymſelfe compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed aboute wyth thoſe that ouerruled hym, beganne to weepe exceadynglye, and proteſted, that he would not depart thence, pronouncyng theſe wordes with the teares in hys eyes. Wherefore wyll ye carye me hence where I fynde my ſelfe well? What neade is there thus to putte on armour? Yf it bee for religion, I wyll take order for it as I ſhall ware elder: In the meane ſeaſon why doe not menne obſerue the lawes? Alas lette no manne trouble my ſtate. Men knowe that after the Queene had roundly declared, that ſhe wold not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the ſaid Fontainbleau: Theſe wordes folowyng were ſayde vnto her: Madame, of neceſſitye you muſte come, and whanne you wyll not ſoo dooe, we ſhall bee conſtrayned to carye the kynge wyth vs. To conclude, menne knowe that vppon thys matter, and after the Queenes reſiſtence, after the teares and ſighynges of the kinge, they were bothe
<pb facs="tcp:11440:10"/> led awaye, fyrſt to the caſtell of Melune, nexte to the caſtelle of Vincenes, and laſtely into Parys, beeyng continually compaſſed about with the ſayde armye, and all the force of footemen and horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that ſynce that tyme haue bene aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled there.</p>
            <p>Herevpon nowe let men without af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection iudge of the controuerſie wherin we differ, to wete, whether the kynge and Queene be at thys tyme in libertie, or rather in captiuitie: whether theyr willes be free, or in bondage: whether they maye go to ſuche places to lye at, as to theymſelues ſeemes good, or not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be caryed and withholden agaynſte their good pleaſure and contentation.</p>
            <p>Surelye all men (yea though they haue but a commune ſence or vnderſtanding) doe call to be in captiuitie:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVHAN A MANNE</hi> after he hathe bene beſette not onelye contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye to hys truſte and opinion, but alſo againſte hys expreſſe pleaſure, by men that withoute comparyſon are ſtronger than hymſelfe: In ſteede of goynge to
<pb facs="tcp:11440:10"/> one place, whereto he hathe appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to goe, is not onelye lette from go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng thyther, but alſo broughte backe agayne, and ledde a contrarye waye: menne calle it alſo a captiuitie whan a man is ſo muche a priſoner, as he can no more bee able to flye ouer a rampiers of piſtoliers and harquebuſiers than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the toppe of a caſtell, beynge either ſtone or brycke: To be ſhorte, menne calle it a captiuitie whanne one is ſoo muche afrayde thorough the dreade of armed perſonnes, as he dare not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his wylle in ſuche ſorte, as he woulde doo, the ſame menne beyng fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from hym.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THIS</hi> thynge beeyng welle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydered, lette all menne iudge of this ſeconde poynte, whether to publyſſhe ſuche a Letter in the name of the Kynge, whereby they force hym to ſaye, that he is not in bondage, but in his large and fulle lybertie: whether to make ſuche a Letter to be printed and publyſhed by the ſounde
<pb facs="tcp:11440:11"/> of a trumpet thorough all the Realme, bee not as muche as to abuſe and defyle moſt villainouſely and vnnaturally the name of his maieſtie, and to make the ſame deſpyſed and ſkorned of all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: where neuertheles the ſame ſhuld be holden holye and honorable, and nat to be vſed, but in matter clerely exempt frome all paſſion and affection of men, (as muche as is poſſible.) Lette men alſo iudge, whether the wytneſſe of a perſone that is reported to bee captiue through conſtraint and violence, oughte to haue ſuche a credite as to iuſtifie the doyng of thoſe by whome it is ſayd, that the ſame is withholden: Chiefly whan the queſtion is of ſuche age and ſexe as oure ennemies deale withall. But lett thoſe, that woulde artificially cloke and coloure this theyr deede, remembre al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to make anſwere vnto theſe thre poyntes: Fyrſt, wherfore the houſe of Guyſe haue armed theym ſelues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a peaſible Realme, that was full of reſte and quietneſſe: Secondely, who they bee that enforced the Kyng and
<pb facs="tcp:11440:11"/> Quene to wepe and lament at Fontain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleau: Laſtly, wherfore the Queene go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on her iorney to Orleance &amp; Blois, was compelled to turne back with thret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, that in caſe ſhe wolde nat ſo doo, they woulde carye the kynge awaye with them. Lette this ſhame and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie than whyche they haue doone to the maieſtie of the kyngs name be accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for one mattier. but immediatly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ther folowed an other. For the houſe of Guyſe, and thoſe of their faction per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing that the people complayned and lamented ouer the thraldom and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of theyr kyng, very wittyly deuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed an inuencion vtterly contrary: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che was to publyſhe, that the Prince of Conde was priſoner in the town of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leance. And to geue colour and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to theyr aſſemble of ſouldiors, haue ſo vyllainouſly played with the name of the Kynge (euen as with a babyll or cockſcombe) that they haue cauſed hym to ſay and publyſhe his letters patentes in his name, that the cauſe of gatherinig this people together was, to delyuer his
<pb facs="tcp:11440:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> deare and welbeloued couſyn the prince of Conde out of captiuitie. Nowe I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde of euery man of ſounde iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether this bee not ſo muche as to buffette the kynge: and after to aſke hym, Who is it that ſmote thee? Nat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandyng becauſe we wyll forbeare from all vehemence of ſpeeche, and talke of this matter without any moode or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration, lette vs ſymply compare the ſtate of the kyng, whome we ſay to bee captiue, with the condition of the ſayde Prince: who yet matcheth not hym ſelf with his maieſtie, of whom he is a moſt humble ſeruaunt: but onely to make a iudgement of all lykelyhode, to whyche of both, the name of pryſoner or captife may be ryghtlyer attributed. The kyng is of the age of about a leuen or twelue yeares. The Prynce is a father of fiue chyldren, all lyuyng. When the houſe of Guyſe came wyth all their force to Fountaynbleau, The kyng hadde but his ſymple ordinarye garde: Whanne the Princes and Lordes whyche are at Orleance came to mete with the prince
<pb facs="tcp:11440:12"/> at Meaux, or otherwhere, he had with hym his force wherewith he was dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to ſtrengthen hym ſelfe afore hande in the towne of Parys. All thoſe of the faccion of Guyſe came with one ſhuffe and in one troupe to Fontaynebleau. The lordes that ar with the prince came to fynde hym one after an other, and frome places farre a ſundre. The kyng and the Queene his mother, dyd many and dyuers tymes commaunde all thoſe that bee aboute theym to leaue of theyr armoure, and expreſly forbadde theym commyng to the courſe with harneiſſed arme: The Prince becauſe he woulde warraunte hym ſelfe frome the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſte whyche he ſawe commynge, ſent and ſente agayne, as welle ſomme of the noble menne of his companye as others, to requeſte all menne, that camme to hym, that they woulde comme ſtronge and welle accoumpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed. Thoſe that are aboute the kyng waſte his good, and ſucke out the ſmall remnant that was in his treaſure to ſatiſfie theyr creditoures: The noble
<pb facs="tcp:11440:13"/> menne that are at Orleaunce, are there vpon their owne coſtes and charges, yea almoſte euery gentylman that there is.</p>
            <p>Thoſe of the faccion of Guiſe, payne themſelues to cauſe ſtraungers come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the realme, wythoute hauing eyther compaſſyon of the poore haried people, or reſpect to the manifeſt peryll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of maye folowe: Thoſe of Orleaunce proteſt that althoughe ſtrangers would come to theyr ſuccours, yet they would rather ſpare the countrey of the Kynge and his poore ſubiectes, thanne theyr owne proper lyues. To be ſhort, thoſe at Orleaunce offer to laye downe all weapon, and to take leaue of the prince to wythdrawe theymſelues euerye man to hys owne, condicyonallye that they whyche detayne the kyng and the quene hys mother, woulde firſt putte of their armour and gyue good exaumple: The houſe of Guiſe and theyr companions, lette not to ſaye dayelye in the hearyng of all the worlde, that they wyll rather ſee the aſhes of all the realme, than to go from the kynges perſonne the dyſtance
<pb facs="tcp:11440:13"/> of .i. league.</p>
            <p>Now lette all men iudge what lykeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode here is, nay rather what infamye it is, thus to prophane and abuſe the name of the kyng, and to make hym ſay by his letters patentes, that his dere and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued cooſyn, the Prynce of Conde is priſoner at Orleaunce: and that for the delyuerie of hym he is conſtrayned to calle together his ban and ariere ban. But lette vs admytte, that it were ſo. Yf the Prynce of Conde be withholden pryſoner, what rebuke haue they cauſed the kynge to receiue, and what iniuſtice haue they don, to declare the ſaid prince a rebell and culpable of treaſon, becauſe he came not to the courte nor laid doune weapon whanne they ſente to hym ſo to doe? For in good logicke they bee thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges repugnaunt, to bee kepte agaynſte his wyll as a pryſoner in a toune, and to deſerue to be proclaimed a rebell bicauſe he commeth not thence.</p>
            <p>Theſe thynges conſidered, it is eaſye to conclude, fyrſte that the kyng and the Queene hys mother wyth the Duke of
<pb facs="tcp:11440:14"/> Orleaunce, haue by a deuiſe of longe tyme handeled and contriued, bene vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentlye and forceablye ſeaſed, caried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye and poſſeſſed agaynſte their wyll and pleaſure, by thoſe who thorough theyr inſaciable greedineſſe declare how fayne they woulde bee hys ſucceſſours: Secondarily, that the aboue ſayde let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters patentes in the whyche it is ſayde that the kynge is in his full libertye, and the Prynce a pryſoner, is none other thanne a manifeſte reproch agaynſte the maieſtye of the name of the kynge the whyche by this meanes is wyckedlye, vyllanouſly, and ſhamefully, defiled and layde abroade to all ſtraunge nations to bee mocked, defamed, and taunted.</p>
            <p>And that for thys reſpecte, none canne bee holden nor eſteemed to bee a trewe Frenche manne, a good ſubiect, and faythefull ſeruaunt to hys maieſtye:</p>
            <p>Oneleſſe wyth all thoſe good and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt meanes poſſyble, and accordyng to the degree of hys callyng, he doe ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour hym ſelfe to reſtore hym to his full power and lybertie, and to delyuer hys
<pb facs="tcp:11440:14"/> name from that reproche and vnwoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyneſſe whiche they haue cauſed hym to receiue in this his minoritie. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth we truſte his maieſtye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge comme to full age wyll fynde hym ſelfe touched, as well to the venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce of his enemies as to the iuſte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardyng of hys good and lawfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes and ſubiectes.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
